[Music]
great so now I want to introduce a notion of
something called the optimal value function
so any questions about the the bman equations
all crystal clear right so if I give an mdp
and ask you to form the vman equation solve it
and give me the value function V Pi can you do
that I'll give you a pi also can you solve it
and give me a v Pi huh maybe here too many to
Compu what of
computers come on I'm going to at some point
I'm going to give you like mdps with millions
of states and ask you to compute value functions
or that don't try to do that with pencil and paper
right so maybe we should give them the head
management program you think we should did you
do the head management when you did the course
I don't you don't think so okay fine so that's
that's a problem that we formulated when I was uh
when was a TA for uh Andy right uh so he wanted
people to appreciate how hard it is for uh how
hard it is to solve dynamic programming how how
hardest to solve mdps are large mdps and this was
a problem that was inspired by a real life problem
uh some sheep or Farmers like diary farmers in
New Zealand actually so okay so so they had lots
of cows and they had to decide when to milk cows
and um you know when went to use C for something
else my God in India is now becoming a political
statement right but uh yeah so okay sheep sheep
okay so so when when you when you milk the cow
and when do you uh retire the cows you know so
so they have to figure out so let's assume that
cows have a retirement home and and so that's a
that's that's a problem so then the cows could
be young you know they could be in breedable
they could be old I mean there are like something
like 14 or 17 different states that they had the
cows be in right and then they have rewards
like if you can Milk The Cow in a particular
State then you get so much milk you know if you
milk a cow in a later State the milk comes down
blah blah blah right so whole bunch of things
and there's a small probability that old what
have been classified as old cows also have cough
you know I mean so basically they become milk
and so all kinds of very complex situation and
somebody actually wrote a paper out of wrote a
research paper out of solving this problem how do
you cast it as a as an mdp and then come up with
a way of solving it because when uh in that
case when you actually cast it as an mdp you
ended up with um like a few million variables few
million States not variables a few million States
and how do you go about solving that problem it
was not not at all clear so what we did was we
came up with a very simplified version of it so
where there instead of like 17 states there are
three states in which the C could be right
and the transition Dynamics were much much
simp simplified right so it could from Young it
could become breedable and it could become old
and then from old it could become breedable
again so it doesn't become young right so uh
so so there like a very few transition and so on
so forth but it still turns out that you have to
for computing the exact transition probabilities
right uh you have to come up with a combinatorial
summation right it's it's actually turns out to
be incredibly hard to get the right transition
probabilities just the P alone everything else is
simple we give you what the state is we give you
what the action is right uh just coming up with
the p and the r the exact CL expression for P and
R itself turns out to be very very hard problem
right and it's not a it's not so there are I
don't know about 300 States or something or 158
States it's a small problem right but Computing
that transition probability even when it is just
158 States Computing the transition probability
turns out to require a combinatorial sum right
so it's it's it's a little tricky so many people
actually fail in getting the right transition
probability they would write the correct code
for solving the problem right but then they would
not know how to compute the transition probability
just to get you to appreciate the difficulty
of coming up with that P and therefore you'll
appreciate why reinforcement learning algorithms
are useful because they can work without the
p
so what is optimal here what what am
I talking about as being optimal so
we never talked about that so far right
so what is optimality in the context of
uh mtps or in the context of RL so we
we already talked about optimality in
the context of orl what is optimality in
the context of orl I want a pi such that
for no other Pi can I get a better return than
expected return than this pi right so I want a
PI right
so and I want a pi that is the best
over all Pi what should be the quantity
here but that is not defined we know that
right so the expectation over return doesn't
make sense so what should I do I should qualify
it over a state right I should talk about where
I start the return and then I can take
expectations over that or whatever but
even better I can do this pointwise so what do
I mean by that I can say I need something like
this p p
p okay thanks yeah this is on the flight
translation problems Edition one has RT
Capital RT is written okay and addition to
g capital GT is written anyway so this is
this is what I'm looking for right and
we know what that quantity inside there
is
right so pointwise I'm trying to
find Max over Pi V Pi of s for all this right
so this is I want a state I mean I want a policy
that achieves the maximum value for every
state right so and I'm going to call this
yeah I'm going to call this P
Star right if I yeah I can do
Ariz so one thing one cave had to note here
is that AR Max might not return a unique Pi
that could be multiple policies for which
this Maxima is achieved in which case any
one of them can be called the optimal policy so
there is no the optimal policy right but there
is a optimal policy that could be multiple
optimal policies just remember that very
simple example I can give you think of uh like
a grid world so this is something we'll revisit
often right let's say that every
state has four actions I can go up
down left or right and every action
is going to get a reward of minus
one right and uh in a deterministic world so
if I go up I'll move up by one square and if
I go right I'll go right by one square and
so on so forth like like in the indicated
directions or you could think of a stochastic
world where you try to go up with probability
Point 9 I'll go up with probability point1 I'll
just stay where I am right you can think of this
as some Wheels slipping when you have a bot
that's trying to move forward and with some
probability the wheels slip and then you stay
in the same same place and you probably have
to try moving again and again until you succeed
right so you could think of it that way right so
that's a stochastic world and every time you
make an action regardless of whether you move
or not you get a minus one right so if you try
to go up in the top row what will happen will
you stay there you'll stay there whether the
action succeeds or not you'll stay there and
you'll get a ro of minus one okay so and this is
episodic task right the whole thing will end when
you reach the state Mark G right so what would
be behaving optimally here we and get to G as
quickly as possible right so the shortest path
to G right so that that is be the optimal way
of behaving in this world right so how many
optimal ways are there of behaving in this
world a policy mapping from states to actions
right doesn't matter where they start from right
this is the maress here right so we assuming
everything is Marco it really shouldn't depend
on where I start from right so so regardless of
where I start from for example when I'm here the
optimal action is to go this way right I don't
care whether I started here and came here or
whether I'm starting here or not right regardless
of where I'm starting the action is like that
likewise okay Things become interesting from
here my God look at the number of
optimal policies we have huh so any
one of these states I can choose any one of those
actions right so basically I have now 12 States
and I can to choose any of the two actions in
those 12 States right so I have a huge number
of optimal policies right and you can convince
yourself this are optimal because they will take
me to the expected number of steps if it's the
deterministic world I can tell you exactly
how many steps it will take me but if it's
a stochastic World depending on what is the
probability of failure of the action right uh
I'll have some probability of reaching the goal
right so great so okay there are too many optimal
policies is there something
common across all these
policies number okay can you can you refresh that
the number of steps it moves to the right is the
same in all the policies okay not in terms
of steps terms of something else that we know
the net reward is the net reward the expected
reward is going to be the same so for any state
regardless of what is the optimal policy I choose
to execute the value of the state will be the
same correct is that clear regardless
of the policy I choose to execute the
value of the state is going to be
the same correct so I can write
this I got rid of the P star here
I'm going to call this V Star and
V Star is unique given an mdp V Star will be
unique right P star need not be unique
but regardless of how many different P
Stars you have right V Star is going to be
the same whichever Pi star you consider V
Pi star will be the same so regardless
of V Pi star regardless of the P star
you choose I'm going to call the optimal value
function as V Star okay so this is called the
okay so this is an optimal
policy it's optimal value function okay is is it
clear
there's only one thing which you
guys should be asking me now how
do I know that the same P
will reach the max across
all so if you have finite mdps it's actually
straightforward to show that okay if you have
continuous mdps right then it becomes a little
trickier uh so we we will discuss this when I'm
actually starting the proofs in the next class
why is it that there exists a optimal policy at
all right so we we'll discuss this in the next
class when I'm talking about proofs right so
right now we'll try to do the equivalent of belman
equations for V Star right I mean like likewise
I can define an optimal value function for Q
what would be the optimal value function for
Q
H
sorry s
Comm
something sound doesn't sound
right right so what is problem
here so we need to put that Pi thing
here right
right so what I what I want you to
appreciate here is that even though
I'm talking about optimal policies
I still the first action I take is
here right so first action I take is
always a whether I'm talking about
optimal so it's only after I take a I
behave optimally so that is why this
Max is after in fact I can remove
the Max from here and I can insert
it anything that comes before that is
not influenced by the max right because
I take a fixed action a okay this is
something which you have to keep in
mind so whenever you talk about Q star
s comma a right the a is still fixed it
might not be the best a to do right in fact
I can have a qar a defined for this action
here right I can have a qar a
defined for this action also
for each one of these actions I can have a Q star
defined right you see that so the Q star of
the down action will essentially be minus1
plus V Star of going from here to the
goal right and the Q star of this action
will be minus1 plus the V Star of going here
assuming it is deterministic otherwise it will
be9 - 1 +.9 * the value of going from here and 0.1
* the value of going from it if it is stochastic
right so so I can think of defining Q star for
even optimal action this is one thing which I
want to keep in mind so it's not like Q is defined
only for optimal actions okay is that clear okay
great so now we have these things so let us try
to see what we can do so I want to do V Star of s
right I want to find V Star of s uh so what would
V Star of s be equal to you think in terms of Q
star
there's no P here so what do you
think V Star of s will be in terms of
qar so what does qar tell me if I take action
a and behave optimally thereafter right so what
can wear B I mean that is essentially behaving
optimally from the current state right so I'm
going to look at okay which one Whatever gives
me the best reward on taking a and then behaving
optimally thereafter right so think about what
this expression is right this expression is
essentially okay I behave according to a and
after that I behave optimally right so that
is essentially this expression right and I'm
taking a Max here which essentially means that
okay which is the action that gives me this the
best of this expression and that I can't behave
more optimally than that because it's only the
first action I have a choice here after that
I'm assuming I'm behaving optimally whatever is
the optimal Behavior right so I'm not talking
about recovering the optimal Behavior yet right
I'm only talking about finding what the optimal
value function is right I'm assuming after
action a I'm behaving optimally so now the
only thing I need to figure out is what is action
a and I need to pick that action a says that when
I add the reward for taking immediate reward
for taking action a and the return for behaving
optimally thereafter I get the most right so this
is essentially very intuitive way of defining what
the optimal value function is now I can expand
this I can say it's Max over a summation S Prime
that's what Max over Pi is
Right Max Pi V Pi is V Star
soar
is it clear how we got that right so this
is called the belman optimality equation for
v
likewise you can write a b optimality equation
for qar qar not be uni ACR all they
have to be why not unique some over
there
why would it some policy there's no question
of some policy will give you a higher policy
I mean why I given you all the optimal
policies tell me which one would do
that so just just think about it if
that is some policy that will do that
then I'll basically change the action to
that I mean that has to be optimal right
if that is it's going right is doesn't have
the same value as going up going up has a
higher value than going right then going
up has to be optimal going right cannot
be optimal because then if I do the
max only one will the other one won't
appear right yeah so one other thing so I've been
talking only about deterministic optimal policies
right I said there are like there are 12 elements
and there are two options there they not be so
as long as I have a policy which assigns only
non-zero probabilities to the optimal actions
right that's also an optimal policy so in this
state I can choose with probability .5 to go up
or probability .5 to go right right so5 go up5
go right that's also an optimal policy right it
could be any combination as long as I have zero
probability for going right or going down right
then I'm happy then it's is an optimal policy
right so there's an infinite number of optimal
policies hm there's infinite number of
optimal policies there is it clear okay
so now here is the next question
I want to ask so given a policy
so given a value function how will
you recover a optimal policy from
that
I give you V Star so how will you
recover an optimal policy from
that so I have to know figure out
what action I have to take in each
state right and I have to take that action
that achieves the the max right so what do
I mean by achieves the max so in the case
of V Star I should take an action figure
out where I land up it right and take that
action that gives me the max over that right
so what I mean by where I land up it so I
pick some action right then I sum over S
Prime
sorry right so this is the utility for taking
an action right so I have to
pick an action that gives me
the so given a V Star this is how I'll recover
a p Star right probab yeah depends on how you
how you implement the argmax right if the argmax
you can write it such a way that it return any of
the maximizers then you'll get a deterministic
policy or you can return your argmax say that
it returns all the maximizers then you can
think of having some kind of whatever some
some probability distribution over the maximizer
it can be uniform or it could be one way or the
other but if you think of AR Max as returning
arbitrarily returning one one of the maximizers
you'll get a deterministic policy right this
is one way of recovering optimal policies from
the optimal value function okay so a little
tricky right I still need to know p and I
need to know the expected values and other
things even if somebody gives me the value
function I still need to know the rest of the
parameters of the mdp for me to recover the
optimal policy but suppose somebody gives me
the Q function how will I recover the optimal
policy if we think about look at the expression
there right in the argmax is exactly this right
so
so if I give you the Q functions if I give
you Q star I don't need all this that what
I'm doing that is essentially looking ahead
one step right if I do a okay what will happen
right so I'm looking at the outcome and then
trying to make the decision the best decision
based on that outcome right but here in the
Q star I don't even have to do that one step
look ahead right I can just be greedy with
respect to my current Q star and I will get P
star okay make sense right so if I
give you V Star and qar now we can
know how to find pi star okay and we also
we spoke about how you can solve the belman
equation for v pi and Q Pi can you solve
the bman equation like that for V Star and
qar so I have a system of n equations in N
variables same thing as before can I solve
it what's the problem it's not linear right so
it's I have this Max here makes it a nonlinear
system of equations so we have to figure out
how we going to solve it right so this is
what we will look at in the next class so next
class what I'll do is first show that uh well
in multiple ways show that V Pi is unique
and then show that V Star is unique right
and then come up with a talk about multiple
ways of solving for V Star and uh well not VP
you can solve but we'll talk about multiple
ways of solving for V Star okay in fact the
rest of the course in some sense is figuring
out multiple ways of solving for V Star and
qar under different assumptions okay how
much information you have how much data
you have and so on so forth right so great so any
questions so far so we're [Music] [Applause] done